awesome
we're good to go well welcome back john
it's very nice to see you again
it's a very good it's very good to be
back i thought our last conversation was
just great
so i'm very pleased to be here yeah and
i think we've built a i was just saying
i think we've built a good foundation to
kind of take some next steps on
so honestly just right off the bat i
think the easiest place to start this is
if you have not seen
the first conversation that we had
together uh that is
required reading for this because we're
going to kind of just take it with a
running start but
i might do a two-minute summary for
people
just to give a sense of kind of where
we're at because i think we came to a
really nice end point with our last
conversation
so the kind of arc we took was
by nature of being human you know a
thinking
thing in a body you are always
confronted with perennial problems
these are always there always lurking
they adapt to you as you adapt to them
and
left unattended either one or many
these can actually be a highly
detrimental force to an individual
a community a culture at large they can
actually be
on the level of an existential threat
for the long-term viability of these
things
and you know as they get left unattended
as the kind of weeds grow
you end up with something like a meaning
crisis
right something where there's just
rampant confusion
isolation all these things that that
stem from this
and so okay you know humans are highly
adaptable machines you know we're not
going to stand there and just take the
punches
and so to address these things we
actually do have some responses
we have psychotechnologies ecologies of
practices
you know spiritual and religious
activities communities that
you know much like the perennial
problems can be adaptive
grow with us scale in size and number so
that we can actually do this kind of
dance with chaos right and actually you
know stay functional stay healthy and
stay smart and another thing that's i
think important with them
is all of those things are non-physical
in nature right they're not an actual
tool that you hold they're a mental tool
because
all of the problems that we have are
non-physical
in nature or at least the perennial
problems that we were highlighting
they're just
you know things that come on a on a
spiritual level on a communal level
and so then you know we we basically
spoke about well when a
group of people come together to
cultivate those things and put them into
practice
it looks very much like a religion yes
yes
and uh so cool so that's basically what
we need right now because we also
you know gave light to the fact that
we're probably in the middle of one of
these right now
there are a number of things coming up
that are becoming increasingly untenable
uh if left alone and so you know some
work needs to be done
and why does it need to be done because
the culture as it stands right now
arguably is generating a lot of these
things and if it continues on this path
that's probably not a way we want to go
so we actually want this thing
and want to create this thing to kind of
bottom up usurp and steal the culture
back in a way that
actually prioritizes the individuals
they're flourishing and the
you know collective well-being of the
whole well said
very well said and we kind of topped it
off with a little cherry of well how do
we do that we have
some avenues we have the logos flow
states circling communities at large the
serious play
actually architecting the culture that
we want to live in
and so then that leads us here today you
know
the the way i was just bringing it up to
you is a lot of that
a lot of that first conversation was
making the case for the what and the why
right what is actually going on here and
a why should we care
and again i think if you care about
yourself others in the world
you should actually have some skin in
the game here because it's
it's on that level of importance but
what i notice both in myself and in
others in this space is
you know there can be this showing up
where you have this motivation
you're hungry you're like yes i want to
do this like let's go do this you know
i'm in
tell me what to do and that that almost
becomes the problem is we
show up here and there's this kind of
gaping void of well
i don't know what to do you know i i
don't know what tools i have i don't
know where the other people are
and there's this kind of yawning opening
that that
spawns up so i hope that and again this
is a little more
uncharted territory here but i hope that
we can
like fumble our way into yeah here are
some of the tools you have here are some
of the ways you can think about doing
this here's some of the
scaffolding you have and if you can
start filling that in
you know you might and through some
iterations we might actually you know
have something that looks like a
cohesive coherent answer to this
great that sounds fantastic so one of
the things
that i think will be important that we
kind of just brushed over last
time so we did the whole ecologies of
practices psychotechnologies what they
are
how they can be used why they're
important but you and jordan hall
have also been covering some really
interesting ground
on the metacyca technology and i'd love
if you could just
delineate that a little more explore
that because i think
that will be uh you know we were kind of
talking about this starting point where
do i start from what do i have
that feels in that in that realm
okay thanks eric um by the way just
great summary
great uh great setup um so
yeah i mean i've been doing some
discussions with jordan hall
and then four-way discussions with
jordan hall
guy sensed christopher master pietro
also
some three-way discussions with andrew
sweeney and with chris with andrew
sweeney and zach stein
so you know doing a lot of this uh
working it out uh
and also exemplifying it um for people
and and the uh my main partner in this
work is chris christopher master pietro
uh we're putting together right now an
anthology
of uh the the major players in this
movement
awesome it's called inner and outer
dialogues uh
the the anthology is going to be done
soon it will introduce you to all of
this
uh the dialogos and dialectic
and then a whole family of practices
like dialectic uh for trying to put you
into
uh dialogues um you know guy is going to
be there
chris and i have written stuff uh thomas
and elizabeth
uh from evolve uh taylor barrett who's
doing stuff
on uh bringing an experimental model in
uh nora bateson in a warm data lab
a ton of people okay so
there's going to be there's a resource
that's being generated right now and
it's going to be
uh done soon that will basically do two
things it will introduce you
to this whole area and this topic
introduce you to the main players their
main ideas uh
so you can pursue them individually and
also
see how they could be put together so
i'm going to try and speak
to sort of at that level uh i'll of
course i have to
i have to give emphasis to my own
particular thing because that's what i
know
more intimately but i do want it
understood that when i talk about
dialectic
and how it affords via logos i i'm not
making an exclusive claim here
in fact i see it as belonging to a
family that's exemplified
in this anthology now and another thing
about
there's one sense in which i think
you're absolutely right and it's
appropriate to start here
but so the order of intelligibility in
the order of explanation is not the
pedagogical order
at all right uh the or in the sense of
the order of training
so you don't start with dialectic
as as your training that's not that's
not
how i see it there's a pedagogical
program you would engage in
in order to undertake it so we'll keep
we can come back to that but i want to
understand that
yes i think this is a good place to
start the discussion i don't want it
understood that this is the place where
you would
start to answer the question you asked
me how do i get started
okay so let's be clear that we're this
is a good place to start the discussion
but this is not the the the you know the
the best
the initial answer to how do i get
started so the idea
and i do and you're right i do owe the
emergence of my
this idea uh appropriately enough to a
dialogue i was having with jordan hall
um two and i have become good friends
and uh jordan was talking about the need
for a meta psycho technology
and the idea here is what a metacycle
technology is
it's a technology it's a a higher order
technology
that whose main function is to help you
collect and curate practices and
coordinate them
and we talked a bit about you know how
to coordinate the practices
within an ecology of practices and the
idea is it's going to help you collect
curate coordinate vet particular
practices
so that you get a viable ecology of
practice
viable in two directions viable for you
individually
and viable so that you can share it with
other people
it doesn't mean that everybody will have
the same ecology of practices
there's there's going to be right very
much it's
it's it's a pluralistic model not a
relativistic model
a pluralistic model in which people are
going to have shared principles
shared sort of vocabulary and grammar
for how they put the ecologies together
and then they'll have different i'll
share this set but with you and
this set with her and youtube like it's
like the way families
right when you look at a bunch of people
they don't all look the same
they share overlapping features and they
all belong together
so that's the that's the model i want
for people to understand
this so the idea here is why would it be
a meta psychotechnology well it's a
metacycle technology
because it's going to be the place where
we can most directly
cultivate in a mutually sustaining and
mutually affording fashion
both individual wisdom and collective
wisdom
so we're going to try and coordinate how
we bootstrap individual intelligence
into individual wisdom and that's going
to be coordinated with how we bootstrap
collective intelligence the collective
intelligence within distributed
cognition
up into collective wisdom and the idea
is that's kind of the best we have
that's the best place we can turn to in
order to get
guidance in order to get well wisdom
in how we can choose
and you know collect curate
coordinate various practices into what
ecology practice so the idea is
um that uh dialectic is the
practice and then deal logos is the
process it ensues
so the idea is that dialectic
insofar as it regularly reliably affords
uh getting into the logos is going to
give you things that will
help to counteract all the negative
effects of
the autodidactic religion of me that
people
fall into uh so which tends to
exacerbate
self-deceptive self-destructive uh
patterns it it can
enhance narcissism which is very
dangerous it contributes to a sense of
fragmentation and isolation
i understand why people do it the
reasons we talked about at length
last time but the idea is it will help
uh counteract that it will also be a
place in which people can practice
and also deeply experience those
enhanced connections
that enhanced religio we talked about
last time
you know the enhanced sense of
connectedness to themselves teaching to
each other
and the world what's amazing when people
get into these practices is
they discover a kind of intimacy
that is uh it's not
of course it's not sexual intimacy or
anything like that
but it's it's kind it's the adjective is
uh
the adjective that should be used has
the wrong meaning
because what happens is people become
more intimate with
the with intelligibility with how
they're making sense
and how the world can make sense to them
and how they can make sense to each
other and all those three
intelligibilities
um are are intermixing so the adjective
i would
should use for syntactic reasons to talk
about the intimacy
is intellectual intimacy but that just
sounds totally wrong
um and so that's why i don't use it so
it's something more like yeah i know
what was captured
in the greek term philia that sense of
reciprocal
intimacy of making sense with each other
together
and it's a so what we're trying to do is
literally enact philia
of sophia of wisdom and so
the point is that dialectic has both um
a group aspect to it and an individual
practice aspect so it also helps you to
bridge
between community and
individual practice and that's good
because we want to always keep the
tension
the creative tension between
individuation and participation
going and so it helps people to bridge
it helps them to see
how they can fit in to a larger
community
and then also how that larger community
can fit into them
so it helps to bridge uh that way
and so it also helps to build those
communities
and those communities are going to be
important
for people to make most of the
transformations they're actually seeking
because most of the way we grow is
through other people both in the sense
of going through them and by means of
them
and so the those are the reasons why
dialectic it's a it's a it's a
psychotechnology
but it's a metacycle technology because
the process
it engenders the logos is so central
to uh addressing all of these concerns
about how we would create an ecology of
practices
and situate it within a sangha within a
supportive community
in which people are meeting together to
regularly
edify challenge and promote each other's
growth
yeah beautiful and again this this theme
this came up a lot in the first
conversation as well and
for very good reason this sense of the
dynamic reorganizing feedback loop and i
think that is one of
i've i've heard in one of these
conversations you know i think
that is one of the central not central
but
um major obstacles with the
classic established religions today is
that there is almost an entire
lack of that that feedback loop it is
very much just one way and in that sense
you know there is no there is no
steering there is no
turning or realigning and yeah i think
that was a beautiful explanation and
one of the other reasons that came up
for me was just
there's a there's a growing sense of
time is of the essence here
you know we should have been doing this
a long time ago and we're still just
trying to agree on the rules and stuff
and so if we're going to do anything we
should have some reasonable expectation
that it's going to
at least be our best shot at this moment
yeah
right and if we don't have a way of
actually discerning that and then taking
action on it well that's almost a
non-starter from the beginning this
isn't exactly just a spray and pray
formula that we want to use we want to
have some semblance of okay
vetting and enacting and again getting
that quick
feedback and so yeah that does seem like
a
yeah i think you know i think i mean
that's one of jordan hall's
i think excellent points he keeps
pointing out
i like myself jordan is very respectful
of the traditional religions
but also like myself he thinks
the urgency of the the issues that we're
facing
and how those issues are themselves
dynamically complexifying issues
they're right there they're they are
evolving
and they're evolving it to become ever
more complex
at an ever increasing rate and so uh
the way again again with much respect
even reverence
for uh you know of the established or
traditional
uh wisdom traditions and religions right
we have to also
i agree with him what we need something
different now
we need something that's a difference in
kind because the difference in the
degree of change is so great that we
need a difference of
kind so we need to try and think about
how to put this together
in a way that has a corresponding
capacity
for dynamic evolution so that we can
constantly as you said
dance with the emerging chaos uh in an
effective and adaptive manner
yeah yeah absolutely and so one of the
one of the groups i want to bring up
into this because i feel like they dance
around
the outskirts of this and at least in in
my vantage point are growing
both as a as a positive side and as a
end as a negative side which is the
growing spiritual but not religious
group um i have my own
thoughts on kind of this group and and
how
how it plays into all of this but do you
have any do you have any initial
thoughts in hearing that
like where yeah yeah so i think i mean
there's a sense in which the spiritual
but not religious are the people that
i'm most trying to reach
uh because with with this idea of the
religion that's not a religion because i
understand
well i'm sorry i don't mean its own
pretentious i think i have a fairly good
understanding
of where they're at and where they're
coming from
so on the one hand to say they're
not religious what do they mean by
saying they're not religious let's let's
work it that way
what they typically mean is they don't
want to belong to any organization
that has any kind of political structure
any kind
of stable um ideological framework that
has to be
adhered to um now now there's mistakes
in that
but let's let's try and pick up on
what's motivating it well what what's
motivating it is
they have right they have seen
um those con they have seen political
organizations
and ideological uh
world views drenched the world in blood
and continue to do so and they have an
intuition often
sometimes it's more of an explicit
argument that that way of approaching
things
is driving the polarization that is
ripping the you know what ripping the
united states apart
and in some ways that's of course
infecting the rest of the world
it's inevitably going to um so
i understand where that's coming from
why don't they just become
atheists then why don't they just line
up behind sam harris
uh or richard dawkins funny enough
sam harris is actually becoming is this
the right way to say he's becoming more
and more spiritual with time
as things unfold uh but you know what i
mean
why not just become an atheist and just
go
well because first of all the secular
political ideological
uh organizations and movements have been
just as bad in fact
if not worse in drenching the world in
blood so
no right and then the idea that
and this is you know this goes to the
heart of what we talked about last time
there was something in these religions
there were practices
there's an intuitive sense that you know
i i get into these patterns
these self-deceptive self-destructive
patterns and i get disconnected from
myself and other people in the world
and i i don't know how to come how to
integrate
uh aspects of myself um
in a way that seems to take or to
sustain and so i
i i want to be spiritual meaning
typically i want to cultivate
practices of self-transcendence
self-transformation and
that will make me wiser i mean that's
not always the word that's used but i
would argue that's
that's always that's always the concept
that's being used
and so they they get that you know
wisdom is needed and that wisdom isn't
just like
learning knowledge from a book wisdom
it's the kind of knowing that requires
deep transformation and so what they
mean is
well i care about these problems of
meaning and i care about cultivating
wisdom but i'm terrified of both the
religious
past and the political past and i'm
terrified of ideological thinking
and so i'm going to be spiritual but not
religious do you think that's a fair
representation
of what's at work for this group yeah
yeah so so the thing about that
for me is i i understand that problem
and that's why i try to
articulate what i call the religion
that's not a religion
in that it's a religion in that it's
trying to
acknowledge that there's so much from a
religious heritage
that we need uh to we need to exact
but it's also acknowledging that we
don't want to fall into
uh the the the the traditional thinking
patterns
even the secular versions of them well
within you know nazism and communism
because those are to my mind
pseudo-religious ideologies
uh and so we don't want we we want to
somehow do that acceptation without
falling into
any of the any of the totalitarian
temptations
um and populism is also a totalitarian
temptation and it's also
a highly pseudo-religious uh phenomena
and if you don't think so
um look at how people are following
trump i mean it's
right so um so all of that
being the case i i think i take i take
that problem very seriously now
i think the spiritually but not
religious people
are also making some very serious
mistakes
so one of the most serious mistakes is
that tends to
be identified with well this is a purely
individual project
this is something i do on my own i do it
for myself and
that very quickly isn't really not a
religion it's just the religion of me
yeah the religion of me and why my
experiences are sacred
and the things i go through and then the
problem with that
is it has the problems we talked about
earlier that really
really exacerbates all of the dangers of
autodidactism
it locks you into individualism
as an ideology and let's be clear here
i'm not talking about moral
individual responsibility that's
something we all bear
and is inescapable and we are obligated
for that i'm talking about a particular
ideology
of how human beings are and how they
should live that is called individualism
that was
generated historically in the
enlightenment period
and i think that ideology is largely
[ __ ] because most of our development
and most of our cognition is done in
distributed cognition and there's
increasing
evidence that we are much better at
growing and overcoming self-deception
in distributed cognition we are much
more rational in distributed cognition
than we are in individual cognition now
of course distributed cognition can go
off to rails too
and that's why we have to do what we
were talking about earlier we have to we
have to organize it properly
but i think the idea that well i can do
this individually auto didactically
that's you know you're gonna that that's
gonna be rife with error
secondly it tends to promote
a kind of narcissism it tends to uh
it tends and the individual is
individualism and narcissism
they tend to reinforce each other
because what tends to happen is
people tend to get into the idea that
what i should be doing
is collecting wonderful experiences
that i can put on my little ego trophy
shelf
that show to myself and to anybody who
challenges me
how really unique and special i am
and therefore why you should pay
attention to me or consider me important
even though i haven't done anything
particularly ethically
or epistemically useful or important to
other people
and and and and that's a big big problem
the third thing and these are not
necessarily separate these are only
analytic distinctions they're often
found together
right is the phenomena of spiritual
bypass which is the idea
that i will avoid you know pain
and trauma and deep character flaws and
personality disorders or defects because
but
by being spiritual and i'll just i'll
bypass
all of the messy [ __ ] that
is at the core of human spirituality you
don't think it is
look through the wisdom traditions they
keep
telling people you don't write you you
that that that messy stuff that yucky
stuff
right that is an integral part of
spirituality
and so people use spiritual but not
religious
as a way of engaging in spiritual bypass
and so there's just a lot of dangers
again remember what i said at the
beginning everyone i understand
i i think i have a fairly good
explanation of
why people do this what's their what's
their reasoning and what's the
motivation
but i'm asking everyone now to
understand
equally the dangers and the threats and
that we
we need to pursue an alternative to
spiritual but not religious
yeah yeah that was incredible so many
other things
i have actually a few points to add on
that because that was
absolutely masterful you know and again
there is
i think it is worth acknowledging like
it it is coming from a place of good
faith right it's people's like i do
recognize the need in this because i
probably you know they probably come
from a point where
i didn't have this before all these
things came up as
expected right again wisdom traditions
been talking about this for a while
and so it's like okay i'm going to do
this and then we run into this
like baby in the bathwater thing where
it's like well i don't want to believe
in the
you know resurrection of jesus and these
fairy tales so obviously the whole thing
is bunk
let me go discover all this for myself i
think the biggest point of it that comes
up for me is you know we were just
talking about the
time is of the essence here and it's
like i'm sorry i don't have the time to
wait for you
to make all the mistakes that people
have been making for several thousand
years
and they wrote it down they wrote down
the ways to actually like avoid that or
get through it easier
and yet you're just off you know running
around doing all this stuff for yourself
you know you come across the
oh i realized i'm god it's like okay you
know we got to go through this thing
that's going to take up some more time
right right there's there's just all
these things that have been written down
and i think and again one of the ways
that gets avoided
is if you are taking this seriously
because it can be
i think there is this sense of you know
the spiritual world as kind of hippy
dippy nonsense like it's all just flower
stuff but
digging down or taking it seriously
enough it is it can be extremely
difficult
yes you know you're rewriting the way
you view reality you're rewriting your
place and
in the entire story it is not always
easy
and to counter balance that you need
containers
you need containers that are conducive
to do the already difficult work
if you're doing that by yourself and you
don't have the community the container
again it just goes haywire it goes
haywire really quickly and you can
actually do an extreme amount of damage
to yourself this is how you get stuff
like cults too like this is how you get
pretty much ridiculous stuff and
it's like yeah so to your point like
there are real threats and dangers
and the greatest part about that is we
don't actually have to figure out how to
answer those because they've been
answered by
several different traditions for several
thousand years it's like yeah okay like
they are right here and yes again
nothing is perfect
no one is perfect nothing we've ever
made is perfect but that does not mean
by any sense that we can just toss out
the
entire uh utility of it
i think that's well said the difficult
task
is again to as you said respect the good
faith
it's that how do i
and this is again where you're doing
this on your own is not going to be
not a good idea you know you should
so when you you're on one that's like
think about holding in two hands
on one hand you should be looking at
these traditions but you're you're
trying to you have this question
well how do i know what i should take
from these
and also how should i take it from them
yeah and
this is where cognitive science can be a
tremendous help and
science is also something you don't do
autodidactically it's something that you
don't
by getting involved right yeah you may
not want or
want or be able to belong to that
community
but there are many people you know i'm
one of them
who are offering to help bridge who are
offering to help say
here is that cognitive science and here
is how
you can make use of it so you can get
guidance
on how to draw from these traditions
and how you can draw from these
traditions in a way that will ultimately
fit into a scientific worldview
yeah potentially transform it and and
that that's a tricky thing
and it's it it's also interacting with
this other creative
tonos this tension we're trying to
manage between as you said providing
people with containers you've got to
frame
or you're going to hit that you're going
to hit the you're going to hit the frame
problem if you don't frame things
um so totally totally on board with that
but you also want to give
space right you know so that emergence
can happen
precisely because we can't just repeat
the past
that this is where jordan's argument
comes in again uh
and we have to acknowledge that there
are
emerging communities of practice that
are doing what we're talking about
but they're also innovating and coming
up with new ideas like i was just
talking again to him yesterday
my good friend uh rafe kelly and the
kind of things
he's doing uh and so
like trying to get all of that held
properly together
this is again why we need we need
distributed cognition we need the
logos we've got it we've got we've got
to get we got to give it our ver we got
to tap
into our evolving very best of
distributed cognition
in order to help people with these
problems
oh that's beautiful yeah the one thing
that came up there as well
is um what when people do try to to take
stuff because they might actually get to
the point of also acknowledging i was
like okay well the whole thing isn't
isn't nonsense but then you end up with
this
i called it i was writing about this the
other day i called it the mr god tato
head where you just
end up with this mashup of like
christian
neo-buddhist hindu stuff and it just
comes together in this
amorphous blob that actually ends up
making
less sense when they try to articulate
it than any of the individual ones
yeah it drives this sense of well this
is the process of a lifetime
and you know in some ways that point is
valid but in others it's well what are
you actually trying to do here
yeah and again even you know that
question becomes impossible to answer
because they don't
know what they're exactly trying to do
they don't have language for it
they don't know how long it should take
they don't have pathways to actually go
do this
and it's like yes you know your evolving
relationship with life
is an ongoing process but if you're just
trying to you know come into right
relationship with yourself
that doesn't have to be something that
takes eight decades that could actually
be
you know an outcome of a process however
you're not in a community you don't have
the scaffolding to actually do that and
so yeah there's this
growing just no man's land of i'm doing
this but i don't know what i'm doing
why i'm doing it or where i'm going and
it's like again
you know guys we need to we need to get
this together like yesterday we need to
all be able to sit at the table and
again to your point actually be a
contributing player
to the game and not just kind of
fumbling around the game board
i actually need to go from players to
designers we're designing a new one
and if this thing is going to take you a
lifetime well
you're never going to be able to take
your seat at the table with the rest of
us
that's that's well said that's very well
said yeah we
by leah sophia we need the best wisdom
we can come up with the chances that
you're going to get that on your own
uh by being an eclectic dabbler
are very small are very small again
i understand why people are tempted that
way
um and i i want to be responsive to that
but um i agree with you i that that is
not
that is not a good strategy and it's
certainly especially now
uh not a good strategy because of the
exigent
nature of the situation we're in yeah
i have one one line i want to introduce
her from one of your other conversations
i don't even know if it's going to
require a comment
it may very well not but i just love the
way it was said
you spoke a couple weeks ago with uh
junsung kim
yes i say that reasonably
he's uh he is a former student
he is an ongoing ra and ta and
co-authored with me
that and big hat tip to that
conversation the
cognitive science of magic that was
unbelievable one of the lines that came
up
is uh you know religion and spirituality
as practices do not require the
supernatural as a theory to function
that's right and i don't even know if
you have a comment on that but i think
that's
absolutely worth putting in because it
may very well be again there aren't many
current examples of religious spiritual
institutions that don't invoke
some sense of supernatural woo which i
think turns a lot of people away from
them
it does it's not a requirement no it's
not
i mean and you know and the work that
uh i'm doing and the work that jun's
doing the work we're doing together
is gathering increasing empirical
evidence to support that claim by the
way
beautiful okay so there's good
theoretical argument and good empirical
evidence
um part of the problem um i think
is uh i mean
the abrahamic religions were really
successful in
uh sort of getting us to deeply in
believe almost like into the grammar of
how we think about this
uh that um that their model of religion
um was how all religions work and i mean
this caused
so much disaster it was one of many
reasons
why eur european colonialism was so
devastating
uh because the europeans would go into
these other cultures
um they couldn't even find a phenomenon
that was separable out
that they could call religion so they
would have to sort of you know you
force that with sort of the opposite of
pigeonholing extracting something out
that
really shouldn't be extracted out and
then re-understanding it
in terms of a belief system and all this
stuff and you know that was one of the
reasons why
and then often just treating it like
noise and garbage
right and so i think we
should we've got good historical reasons
why we should pause and think about
that but we know that the supernatural
is something that and i talk about this
in my series i give the
uh argument it's something that emerged
historically
within the west um and so
thinking that well that's the way it
just has to be or it's not a religion
it's like okay fine if you don't want to
call it religion if it doesn't have the
supernatural then i'm interested in
religion or something else right i'm
interested in whatever it is that's
enhancing religio
so that people have experiences that
they call are sacred
because they get into right relationship
with what is most ultimately
real about themselves each other and the
world
and if you don't want to call that
religion then fine i don't care but i
think that is the core
of what religions have done and i've
given arguments for that and we have
very clear historical precedence the
neoplatonic tradition
right yes it has right it has
metaphysical levels
but they're not like um our notion of
the supernatural
in fact you can see the some of the
church fathers taking the neoplatonic
tradition
and wrestling it so it fits in right and
and eventually gets
organized into especially people like
aquinas right
gets organized into our category of the
supernatural and
there so first of all that's a
problematic category
second as i've argued i think it's a way
in which
we we sort of legitimated
and ossified the two
i don't know where that noise is coming
from yours or my end
um legitimated and ossified
um the two worlds mythology the idea
that reality
is made up of two fundamentally uh
different worlds um and i
and i again i think that was something i
understand and i
i try to explain why that mythology
arose but the scientific worldview will
not countenance that
um and and if you say well i'm just
going to ignore the scientific worldview
good luck
go try that try that right now during
covet right
what does that mean like i i don't
like all i don't believe this well yeah
yeah you do because you go to the doctor
and you turn on the internet and you use
all of this technology and electricity
and electromagnetism and physics and
chemistry
and by like you can't that's just
pretense okay
now i'm not i'm i'm not arguing for
scientism
i'm not saying that if science is the
only thing or that all of the current
claims of science are true i think
that's ridiculous
but the idea that we can somehow well
i'm just going to ignore
the scientific worldview and i'm just
going to somehow keep
the supernatural the two worlds
mythology that strikes me
as very uh non-viable it's like i said
we have good historical and
cross-cultural reason to suspect that
category
to suspect that that is of the essence
of religion
we have geniuses like platinus and
spinoza
who gave us uh alternatives profound
monisms
ultimately that do not support uh
the dualism of a supernaturalism that
dualism
tended to support an internalized
version of the two worlds
we internalize that dualism as a deep
dualism between mind and body
the mind and body are two separate and
two distinct kind of things
and we were and we sort of reduced
religion into
like very much in the head uh and our
sense of who and what we are
and what we're now discovering both in
cognitive science and the whole rise of
the embodied movement
movement they should come up with a
better name um
is that no that that dualism of mind and
body
it's just not sustainable so we've got
to get rid
of that commitment and so
i think trying to
come up with a way
of being spiritual and you now know that
i don't mean in an auto didactic
individualistic
isolated monological fashion trying to
be spiritual
without recourse to
the supernatural is deeply needed
today it's deeply deeply needed and it
is
i've already given you arguments for why
it's possible
it's definitely possible and it's
already happening it's already happening
so if we can come to a place where
we don't have to invoke we don't have to
invoke or commit to
these powerful kinds of dualisms
these dualisms were originally
functional but the problem is they
became malfunctional
and a dualism that becomes malfunctional
becomes a profound
dichotomous disconnection and it's it
it disconnects you in profound ways
from yourself from each other in the
world and that undermines
the religion the meaning making their
sacredness in a profound way
yeah and actually that visual you just
gave there is a i think a feeling that a
lot of people have coming into this
space it's like i am torn between
these drives or these feelings inside of
me and i just
it's untenable i feel like i'm coming
apart at the end it's like
yeah it's uh it's very true it's always
it always makes me laugh you know
particularly for your whole
meaning crisis series like yeah these
ideas were actually invented
like mind-body dualism wasn't just a
thing that existed
it was actually created and it's like
wow these things have become extremely
extremely ingrained
yeah greg enriquez and i are doing a new
series right now
that's on my youtube channel called
untangling the world not of
consciousness in which we're
going through that history and we're
trying to come up with
a non-dualistic account of the nature
and function of consciousness
as again trying to ultimately address
the meaning crisis beautiful there's a
big uh
there's a big set up folks take note
so and you know we we spoke about this
after we stopped recording in the first
one but i do want to weave in
another another thinker and some
theories into this
that i i've found at least personally
very useful
that of jamie wheel and some of his some
of his work around ethical culture
we talked in the first one about how you
know this kind of religion that's not a
religion and
stealing the culture and the importance
of culture are more of like an
interweaving dna than
than separate initiatives here but a lot
of this conversation a lot of our first
one was around
well we need to get in relationship to
self other and world
and again we bookmarked this whole
beginning as a kind of well
what you know what what do i do i
understand that i need to do that how do
i actually do that
and jamie puts forward and again i think
this wasn't
with some collaboration from you as well
these three pillars of if you're going
to have practices they should probably
address
these three things and i love them
extasis
like a feeling of self-transcendence
connecting to something greater than
yourself
catharsis the kind of deep healing that
comes from that sense of
that we can get of being an isolated
individual and community
communities right the sense that we are
actually in this together all going
through the need for those first two
anything coming up for you around that
yeah i i mean i
i have talked with i give all credit
to jamie and organizing those
i've talked to him i think i had an
extended conversation with with him just
once
and then there's been some email
exchanges um
i i think that's important um
independent of him
i was talking about x-states i have
extensions tattooed on my leg
uh i was talking about extensiveness and
communities uh
for a very long time um now so the the
part that uh
jamie has put more emphasis on uh that i
haven't addressed as much
but um i am turning my attention to
is catharsis uh again with that and
jamie doesn't mean it this way
don't think of it just in the freudian
sense of sort of
right you know the big discharge right
and freudian pun intended um uh so
it's not that um it's it's more of an
aristotelian sense so aristotle invoked
the notion of catharsis
as a way of trying to explain uh the
aesthetic experience and the
transformative experience of
witnessing tragedy a draw a tragic drama
um and so catharsis is properly
understood
as a way in which you are playing with
identity um in order
to release ways in which
you are hurting or in ways in which your
development is being thwarted
or ways in which um you have been
uh wounded uh and
give you a way of
well a syria a serious play
the pun intended there too yeah a
serious play
uh that would allow you uh to start to
break the grammar of how that has become
immovable within you it's it's a way i
talk about overcoming
existential inertia the way in which
these patterns
get locked in and we can't we
they've still reciprocally narrowed us
we talked about this last time
right reciprocal narrowing that was sort
of addicted to the identity we have in
the
in the world we're in and we we don't we
we want i want to be over there
right but we're we're we're we're locked
in and there's a tremendous inertia
that almost like a locomotion you know a
locomotive that just can't get
started because there's a right there
right there's all that inertia
and so that that notion of catharsis i
think is
something that needs to be brought into
this discussion
and i think it needs to be integrated
with
the pursuit of self-transcendence which
is something that uh as you know i've
been emphasizing a lot
and how that connects to what you just
indicated mattering being connected to
something
that has a value beyond your individual
egocentric perspective
um and so that yeah stasis
and and then of course we've been
talking throughout about communitas
all of this stuff about the logos and
dialectic is communicated
but i want to give jamie credit for yeah
the the catharsis element
needs to be properly uh brought in as
well
uh the the danger there
is and this comes up specifically within
specific practices like circling
or like dialectic the danger there
is for these practices to degenerate
into therapy even group therapy
right we're trying to steer between uh
theory and therapy in what we're doing
here uh this sort of skillet and cryptus
and so the really tricky thing is
people like you know what you're
teaching people
to to meditate the brain no the brain
the brain has two
two things it's like uh you close your
eyes oh i know what we're doing we're
mind wandering
yeah yeah you know no no brain that's
not what i'm doing oh i know what we're
doing we're falling asleep no no brain
we're not doing that
and these are the two big options and
you're trying to find that little
you know the narrow path and you're you
know you're trying what you're
largely doing trying to grow the width
and the depth of that
that path with practice right and it's
the same thing here
like people i know we're doing we're
theorizing no no
we're not oh i know what we're doing uh
right we're doing therapy no no we're
not
we're trying to find the space between
those and then widen it and deepen it
uh through practice and so um
yeah bringing in the catharsis uh brings
with it that risk
uh and that's why it's very that's why
i'm doing a lot to try
and situate this uh within
within philia sophia it's it's
interesting because uh iran
have in his work on philosophical
contemplative companionship
does the same thing he says that this is
it it's in the family by the way
the dialectic family he says this is a
group practice you do
that's trying to not be like
philosophical counseling
where you're doing dealing with a
person's individual sort of therapeutic
uh needs and it's not like a philosophy
cafe
where you just get together and talk
about topics you're trying to get the
transformation
from the therapy but you're trying to
get the education
uh that you get from theory and you're
trying to get
like almost like you know scary
stereoscopic vision you're trying to
look through
both into something beyond both of them
yeah that was beautiful i have this um
i have this kind of clunky visual coming
up
it's like a like a pyramid of focus so
we have again at this top this kind of
reinvigorating
religio in both individual collective
you know we come down to the second tier
which is okay well that is done through
right relationship of self other world
which we laid out
and it again one of the reasons i love
jamie's work is because he he seems to
always come from the bottom of the
pyramid while everyone else is coming
from the top
and so then we get this other layer of
like okay well to do that
you can tweak the dials of extasis
catharsis communitas
right to trickle up to that and he
actually
this is all in i just want to give him a
shout out he did a talk called the
potential and pitfalls of
transformational culture
it's up on youtube if you want to see
him riff on this stuff for an hour
please go check that out because it's
amazing
and you know below those dials the three
dials he lays out he actually has
like a kind of five tools that you can
use scripture
sacraments ethics metaphysics and
deities
it's like look if you actually want a
game plan to go build some of this
yourself you know you have your aim
right you have what you're working
towards you have the kind of knobs and
the tools that you can use to do it
get a group together play around talk
about it
put some practices out and then you get
this thing that when iterated over time
becomes
what we've been working towards is like
this
group of people tackling these problems
and actually making some
hopefully making some good headway on
them yeah
i i think that's well said again
i think we need to
do that in some way differently than we
have in the past
because there's always been the
bottom-up aspect and that's good by the
way that there's always been
like you're pointing to um and i think
we need as much cognitive science about
that machinery as we can possibly bring
to bear
um it's so i'm really interested
in both the uh innovations happening
within the cognitive sciences telling us
about
all of this bottom-up machinery and the
top-down but more at the bottom up
and i'm also interested in like
supplementing that with
uh participant observation and
discussion of
the bottom-up emergence of people uh
tweaking these things trying to figure
out
what what will be the kinds of things
that will not be idiosyncratic
to an individual or just to a particular
group um within a particular historical
um or physical environment um you know
this is paul vander clay's issue right
this this has to be
you know scalable it has to be it has to
be something that can be shared
across a lot of the things that normally
divide us
um or else as you've reminded us
repeatedly
we're not going to have what we need in
order to
deal with what is facing us right now
and you know covet well we talked about
this last time it just accelerates
all the issues of the meeting crisis
and it does that and in conjunction with
doing that
it's accelerating a lot of the way in
which things are fracturing and
fragmenting
and i think people are starting to
understand that i think they're
starting to understand it unfortunately
a kind of unhealthy way
people are starting to talk about
pandemic fatigue
people are starting to realize it's not
going back to the way it was before
right that's right and they've been sort
of a lot of people i've got i get the
sense we're holding their breath
i'm waiting right okay now let's go back
um it doesn't look like it doesn't look
like that's
that's the way to frame things right now
and so
what i'm saying is we we need to
again i i feel like i'm repeating myself
but
we need to reach as deeply into the
roots of our tradition
to grow up into the you know the novelty
of the sunlight
um if we're gonna if we're gonna grow
what we need here
uh we have to be doing both uh if we're
gonna if we're gonna really create
something
uh that has the structure uh the growing
structure that we need
uh to address our issues yeah
beautifully said
and i also i've certainly had this sense
in myself and i think
i think it's shared shared by many this
sense of
oh yeah but who am i to do anything
about this what can i actually do what
can i actually contribute
and again i got to shout out jamie on
this i love the little progression that
he gave
he was like what we're actually trying
to do here is we're trying to take as
many people from npcs
like non-player characters actual
players to like show up and play games
maybe again games that have been already
established by people totally cool but
once you're an experienced player
actually becoming an architect
like start building these things with
people and
and the uh like architects of culture
like actually just
show up start doing this you can fumble
around the dark a little bit
again that's also why you know
containers communities are super helpful
so we're not fumbling as much as
possible but it's like
you can always do something with what
you have with where you are
and if you do feel the
a the growing need individually or
collectively you recognize it like
let's go you know there's a seat at the
table for you you're a human on earth
there are enough seats for everyone but
it'd be really wonderful if we all
showed up shared our voice started
playing started building
very much i mean and i want to emphasize
that
and extrapolate a bit on it so
when systems are very stable it's
actually very hard for any individual
part or component
of that system to make much of a
difference because there's all these
redundancies built in there's all these
constraints
but when systems are very destabilized
that they are now
you get what's called sensitive
dependence on initial conditions
a very small difference by an individual
component
can you know butterfly effect out into
the system in ways you can't um
anticipate you know for want of a nail
round of a nail the horse right was
unshod and because the horse was on shot
the message wasn't delivered
because the message wasn't delivered the
battle was lost and because the battle
was lost the kingdom
fell right and so you don't right when
we're
i get it again because we have
again we've developed these world views
and these models that
you know have unfolded across millennia
um you know how old is christianity
right and things like that
um we we get a sense well you know
i can't do much and maybe that was
true uh but i would argue
that's not true now you like you don't
know and the way things just
boom now and then they just take off
like you know i've been doing the uh
the the the weekly morning uh
meditation contemplation you know and as
sanga grew up
i didn't make that happen by the way did
sanger grew up
and then people started forming
relationships and then a discord server
was created
right and then the discord server the
sangers like
like and they just go right don't
try and move the world i'm putting
socrates here
move yourself if everybody moves
themselves
the world moves right and so um
yeah i think uh there
i've been i mean
i'm also influenced by stoicism you
shouldn't inflate how much you can
change
things you've got to be always rational
about it because you can get
uh very inflated um
but i have been again let me try and do
this very carefully let me thread the
needle here
i've been impressed by how my actions
interpenetrated in connection with the
actions of others
and then how that created things so
rapidly and so powerfully
beyond what i foresaw happening
yeah yeah yeah that's worth
that's worth underscoring uh some of the
team and i
over over on these parts have a have a
word that we love it's called
indicated and the way i would describe
it to people is like
if you're standing on a road and it's a
black street
and you don't know where to go you don't
know what to do you don't know what the
next step forward is
if you earnestly search for it both just
with what you can
think yourself through and actually feel
is appropriate
eventually something comes up that's
like one of the street lights
turning on and boom it's like oh okay i
need to move in that direction
a really silly example but can be useful
is like
if you're thinking of you want to take a
trip somewhere and
the next week later your friend comes up
telling you a story about costa rica
and then you see on facebook this this
other story about costa rica you're
like there are a lot of countries in the
world
and only one has come up multiple times
like there's this there's this flashing
alarm this this signal to you
and if you can just take like the next
indicated step
over and over and over again again you
get these massive snowballs where it's
like look
you know there's a pandemic you know
people are kind of freaking out
can i help them meditate sure so
small so simple so basic and yet you
know a couple months down the road we're
now here with this organic
evolving community doing beautiful work
together and it's like well if i tried
to do that at the beginning
maybe i couldn't have hold it like held
that way yeah maybe i just wouldn't have
done it because it would have seemed too
big
but you know if i'm just going on
youtube doing meditations for people
i can do that and again you know we are
such a large
body of people right you can't
underestimate the power of everyone
actually doing that over and over
and over again and if the steps are
small enough you can do daily
you go far and this is again where we've
got to give up
again not i get not individual moral
responsibility but we have to give up
individualism
because i mean this is where jordan hall
i think is bang on
with his slogan the next buddha is the
sangha
the next book is the sangha the only
thing that we're
capable of that will have the cognitive
computational power for solving
the complex issues and at the rate at
which those issues are evolving and
changing
is our very wisest most comprehensive
forms
of distributed cognition yep
you always stand on the shoulders of
humanity you know regardless of where
you are
and i think for a lot of us this is
actually where again religion is
something very useful
those with religion seem to absorb that
very nicely like yes of course i'm part
of this beautiful thing
those of us who are maybe a little more
western scientific is like well no i'm
i'm the self-made man i've done this all
myself
and it's like you use english that you
didn't create
these farming techniques that you never
made like almost
there's very little about you that's
self-made you didn't even make your body
like your parents did that like there's
very little of you that's self-made
it's actually a perspective right that
can that can be empowering or i guess an
obstacle for some but it definitely
doesn't have to be well i mean again
you have to look at these things
historically i mean individualism
as a an ideology arose
to try to counterbalance um the way in
which collectives
can become totalitarian um
and again but it's it's a kind of over
compensation
it's a compensation that has worked by
denying um
uh uh of the the the overwhelming
reality
of distributed cognition so the solution
is
to acknowledge the critiques that
motivated individualism
a propose ways of keeping distributed
cognition wise meaning
dynamically self-correcting so that we
avoid
some of the perils that individualism
rose in response to
yeah beautiful beautiful so i have
two kind of last things i want to bring
up one we've touched a little bit on one
is a little bit
i guess you could say selfish but i
think it's i think it'll end up being
super useful
so actually again inspired by a lot of
your original series
you know i was i was off looking i was
off looking for an answer of like what
does this thing look like
can i find an example of this because
i'm down to like be a player i'm down to
participate in it and see
see if i can you know bring something to
the table there as well
one of the few things that kept coming
up for me over and over again
was yoga yoga as a philosophy and as a
way of being
particularly the way of being thing
because i think
like many things that we've kind of
ported over it's been a little distorted
with the classic
you know monday morning lululemon yoga
mat but that's not exactly what i'm
talking about i'm talking about the much
more robust
philosophy that's endured for again
generations and generations and there
were a few things
in there that appealed to me really
deeply about this that i'd love to just
kind of get your sense on what you think
of so again we talked about self other
world we talked about excesses catharsis
communitas
scripture sacraments ethics metaphysics
deities all of these things
and actually for all the kind of check
boxes that i was looking for
again yoga seemed to be one of the few
things that actually
checked off something near a majority of
them it has a very clear
overarching goal which is basically
recognizing yourself
as the awareness that all things show up
from and recognizing that
as you know basically all that is
cool the thing i found extremely
interesting
was that it actually doesn't force you
into
a path to that realization they're
actually kind of
four larger branches there's an academic
intellectual one where you can come to
that realization through study
of scripture cool there's one of kind of
devotional ritual
where you do prayer chanting dance come
to the same realization totally
different path
there's there is the very classic kind
of self mastery
awkward poses meditation one where you
come to the same realization
and then there's a selfless service like
you know you know
showing up for others and in that way
coming to the same realization
and that felt
like almost something i had never seen
before because
at least in my conception you know a lot
of the other practices a lot of the
other religions was like yo
get on this car take this path it'll
take you here but of course different
people have different dispositions
some are way more intellectual some are
way more in the heart and to have
something that met you where you were at
but took you to the same place
that felt absolutely incredible
and then of course you know it actually
increases
in levels as you go up you know you can
the the classic asana posture practice
is probably the greatest example where
it's like if you're a beginner
it can meet you there and after you've
been studying it for three decades
and are much more have much more mastery
over it you still have in the same
vehicle
a set of practices a way to live your
life
a daily routine that is still just just
as useful for you and that whole flow
from like
the way i spend my tuesdays grows with
me
and leads me to the same thing and i can
do it in a community
i don't know something about that just
feels like resoundingly
hopeful or like wow this could actually
have some serious potential
so i mean i think it's what you said is
well said
uh especially how you prefaced it it's
important i want to return to the caveat
because yoga tai chi chuan
mindfulness practices have all been uh
reduced and commodified
um yeah and
if i mean yoga originally means yoking
it's the same it's it's got the same uh
indoor appearance
indo-european root is conjugal like when
people are having sex
right it's about it's about the art it's
about that kind of falling in love
with that which transcends you uh so
right you are drawn into uh self
transcendence
so um i think all of that is exactly
right
um and i do think that
what you're pointing out is if we ignore
the western reduction there's an ecology
of practices
because even if you're in any one of
these paths you're not just doing
the postures there's a hole so
before my meniere's got bad uh i was
for i had taken up with my partner
she and i were doing yoga regularly and
it was very much
a spiritual practice um and being taught
more in that way of course that varies
with the instructors it was some
instructor
there we have a joke in martial arts of
punch and kick studios
dojos right where all you you just go
there you run a punch and kick
and it's like oh yeah great when you're
15 that's so cool
and when you're 33 that's so useless um
and so to my mind there's some
instructors that are more just punch and
kick yoga
right they're just oh do this and bend
that no
right so but there's people that come in
like what i was talking with tai chi and
like there's a whole ecology of
practices
uh going around it and then and then
what you just pointed out to the
pluralism right
that different people are going to need
because
of their own idiosyncratic timing and
placing
in you know how they are going through
their lives
and the relationships they've formed in
the history they've had and the
woundings they've suffered
um and and the socio economic and
political
structures that they've you know
internalized and
endured right all of those things you
know as well as as you said
you know personality variables etc all
of those things
we just can't ignore them but of course
other traditions have this too um
they're harder to see
but if you take a look for example
within christianity you don't have a
single monastic tradition
you have you know augustinian jesuit
dominican
right you again right and you have and
there's
different mystical traditions even
within those different monastic
traditions
right um and so we
even something that looked like it was
you know
monolithic you know hence the name the
catholic church
like the universal one church it was
very much in practice
uh a very pluralistic uh model and
notice
again you had priests and you had monks
they were even different
uh individuals
so i think if you look carefully this is
not to take anything away from yoga
but i think if you look carefully many
of these traditions
have understood at least in
ortho practices if not in orthodoxy
right they have understood pluralism not
relativism
pluralism and so the degree to which i
think
you saw yoga as giving you
an ecology of practices and
really exemplifying pluralism and
having a pedagogical program of alia
affair yeah of course that's what
that's that sorry i don't mean to
trivialize but my excitement is
yes that has to be i would argue the way
it has to be
what i would say and what i'm trying to
say is i do think the other traditions
have that
but well for reasons we talked about
like last time
the west's connection to its own wisdom
tradition and heritage is seriously
severed and fragmented and malformed um
and so and it's interesting because we
finish
um we're no longer doing as a was it
last friday or the friday before
we i can no longer because my schedule
uh do the weekly morning
process i'm back at university my son's
back at uh
university uh uh my my
tech advisor he's he's getting a new job
which would look great
um so we're now we're now we we're now
no longer doing them
we did 111 how auspicious is that eight
one one one
uh but so uh uh we
we finished the the the weekly morning
classes
uh sorry the the daily morning classes
we now go to a week we're not doing a
weekly
saturday sanger from 10 to 11. but the
point i was trying to make is
so we went through the eastern
traditions we went through
uh you know what we buddhism and the
taoist traditions
and what we can draw from that but now
we're turning to
the western wisdom tradition we're going
through mclennan's book
the wisdom of hypatia and we've learned
epicureanism and now we're doing
stoicism
epicureanism is like sort of primary
school skeptic
it's not skepticism uh stoicism is high
school and then we
we and then you go into neoplatonism
which is like university
and it's amazing how people are
resonating
as profoundly as they did when they
encountered these practices from the
eastern traditions how much they're
resonating
with this which is actually in the roots
of their own
tradition it's really really an uh an
interesting thing to witness
so along again there's a pluralism the
ancient world recognized it
uh the marcus aurelius endowed four
chairs
right uh a chair in aristotelian
philosophy
stoic philosophy epicurean and platonic
he's a stoic but he recognized the need
for pluralism
right again not relativism pluralism
these
all talk to each other they mutually
inform constrain they share
principles etc etc so i think
yeah i think
i think the fact that that so
plugged into you is evidence
for how important
ecologies and practices pedagogical
programs
pluralism how important it is just how
important it is
yeah there we go again this is this is
really what i was hoping to
to kind of explore with this of like
these are the knobs these are the dials
that you can tweak yourself that you can
look for in the world
that if you feel called you could damn
well very well build with other people
right you could build with a community
yeah because it does you know that feels
like the next step
so actually you know i really just have
kind of one thing i want to queue up for
you which is just any other
just any other thoughts you know so we
started the first conversation with
making the case
right building the foundation what is
going on here why should you give a damn
you know we walked through a fair bit
today of okay if you actually
want to answer the call if you actually
want to show up and move
either into being a player of this game
or an architect of the whole game itself
you know here are some things you can
consider here's some dials you can tweak
where do you want to leave people with
like where should someone if they listen
to both of these and they're like
hell yeah like i'm in i'm gonna go build
something amazing i'm gonna build
something super cool with
super cool people where to next
well i mean that's a difficult question
to answer
because of the very thing we talked
about pedagogical programs and pluralism
i mean you need to know where people are
at i think people need to cultivate
a lot of skills both individually and
collectively
uh you know skills of mindfulness uh
skills of rational reflection uh
training of the imagination
uh psychosomatic meaning body mind right
uh like yoga uh skills uh movement
practices uh like that rafe talks a lot
about i i
agree i think those are central to
transformation because of the way
cognition is so embodied
and enacted uh so there's a lot of uh
you need to
individually and collectively
collectively and individually
interpenetrating
individually and collectively you need
to cultivate skills and virtues
uh and so there's lots of places to go
i mean that's why i'm not just doing
these dialogues like i said i offered
the the the the daily morning classes
and now at least the weekly morning
classes
and i'm putting up courses and then
you've got people like rafe kelly who
you know who are organizing or uh chris
and i are putting together
the anthology which will introduce you
to people who are literally creating
ecologies and practices
and communities that you can get
involved with so there's a lot there
but i mean in neoplatonism there's this
wonderful idea
that you you can receive things
according to uh
your degree of receptivity and uh young
said something similar
uh don't don't try and take on a wisdom
that you haven't
earned right um uh uh
and so start where you're at and ask
yourself
really you know what is what ecologies
and practices do i have now what do you
believe
don't tell me what you believe i'm sick
and tired of that
sorry that's a little too rude but like
don't our culture is so drenched
this is what i believe who cares who
cares
right sorry you know what i care about
tell me what you practice
yeah tell me what you practice because
practice
is how you can be transformed and how
you can help others transform
and how together we can transform the
world tell me what you practice
and practice means what do you do that
challenges you to change and development
individually
and collectively review your practices
look at what's out there go to places
where you can learn
to start practicing to acquire the
skills and virtues
that we need in order to move more and
more
towards being wiser wow wow that was
incredible
yeah you know what came up was just uh
show me where you spend your time
attention and money and i'll tell you
what's important to you
yeah exactly and that's true
exactly yeah wow that was that was
extremely beautiful
honestly i don't think i have much more
than that uh that feels
that feels good to me too it feels like
it it it's
at least got the closure of this
particular dialogue yeah
for sure that was incredible well there
you have it folks round two with
jennifer fakey
building the religion that's not a
religion that was really wonderful john
thank you so much uh thank you so much
eric
again this was wonderful i'd be happy to
come back again
i find uh these discussions are
well they're true dear logos we i get to
a place with you that i can't get to on
my own
and i know that
the people that follow my work found our
last
conversation last video tremendously
helpful um
and so thank you once again beautiful
thank you